Leon Kroll
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Correspondence, 1905-1973, Series 2:; (Box 1-4; 3.6 linear feet)
  - Mc-Mi, 1920-1972 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    (Includes letters from Henry McFee (with photograph), Gari Melchers, and Carl Milles)
  - Mo-My, 1920-1972 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    (Includes letters from Marianne Moore, and Jerome and Ethel Myers)
  - National Academy of Design, 1925-1971, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 43-46)
  - National Arts Club, 1930-1971 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, 1943-1947 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1930-1972 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Nebraska Art Association, 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - New York World's Fair, Inc., 1936-1939, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Nichols, Hobart, 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Nichols, June, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Norton Gallery and School of Art, 1945-1948 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Norton, R. H., 1930-1947 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Office of War Information, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Organ, Violet, circa 1930s (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - N-O, 1932-1970 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    (Includes letters from Elias Newman and Ivan Olinsky)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1927-1958 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Pennsylvania Museum of Art, 1925-1935 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Pepsi-Cola's Annual Art Exhibition, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - P. Jackson Higgs, Inc., 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Pregel, Boris, 1945-1961 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Pa-Pe, 1929-1966 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Ph-Pu, 1925-1972 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    (Includes letters from Robert Philipp and Gregorio Prestopino)
  - Ramsy, Lee, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Raphaelson, Samson and Dorshka, 1929-1965 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Rehn, Frank K. M., 1924-1936 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Retail Fine Arts Trade (Art Dealers Code), 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rhode Island School of Design, 1932-1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Robert C. Vose Galleries, 1925-1947 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1960, 1962, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Rowan, Edward, 1935-1944 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Q, Ra-Ri, 1925-1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    (Includes a letter from Diego Rivera)
  - Ro-Ru, 1923-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    (Includes letters from Lucien Rollin)
  - Sackett and Wilhelms, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - San Antonio Art League, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sapiro, Aaron, 1932-1933 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Schnakenberg, Henry, 1936-1939, circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Seide, Charles, 1938-1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Seidman and Fisher, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Smith, Catherine, 1933-1935 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1955-1959 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Speicher, Eugene, 1915-circa 1954 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Springville High School Art Association, 1937-1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - State University of Iowa, 1932-1936 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Stern, Louis, 1932-1950 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Sterne, Maurice and Vera, 1930-1960 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Steuben Glass, 1940-1963 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Stone, Harlan F., 1937-1942 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Strachan, Rose (Mrs. Frank), 1944-1946, circa 1940s (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Studio Publications, Inc., 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Sa-Sf, 1932-1972 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Sh-So, 1933-1973 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    (Includes letters from Nan Sheets, John Sloan, and Raphael Soyer)
  - Sp-Sw, 1927-1970 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    (Includes letters from Leo Stein)
  - Taylor, Francis and Pamela, 1937-1951 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Toledo Museum of Art, 1932-1942 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Treasury Department, Procurement Division, 1933-1938 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - T, 1924-1965 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - United Seamen's Service, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - University of Illinois, 1935-1951 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - University of New Mexico, 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - University of Notre Dame, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Van Veen, Stuyvesant, 1937-1940s (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - U-V, 1930-1972 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    (Includes letters from Theodore Van Soelen)
  - Watson, Forbes, 1931-1947 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Weber, Max, 1922-1923, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Webster, Hutton, 1931-1946 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Weeks, Carl, 1925-1941 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1931-1963 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - William Macbeth, Inc., 1931-1936 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Williams, Esther, 1938-1944 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Wolf, Hamilton, 1938-1942 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Worcester Art Museum, 1937-1942, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Worcester War Memorial Murals, 1934-1944, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 48-50)
  - Works Progress Administration, 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - W. S. Budworth and Son, 1924-1939 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Wyeth, Andrew, 1946-1959 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Wa-We, 1930-1969 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    (Includes letters from Maynard Walker and Harry Watrous)
  - Wh-Wu, 1932-1971 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    (Includes letters from Frank Lloyd Wright)
  - Yaddo, 1932-1935 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Zilboorg, Gregory, 1942-1947 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - X-Z, 1927-1966 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    (Includes letters from Mahonri Young and William Zorach)
  - Unidentified, First Names Only, A-E, 1933-1972 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Unidentified, First Names Only, F-L, 1908-1970 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Unidentified, First Names Only, M-Z, 1940-1972 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Unidentified, Illegible Names and Letter Fragments, 1905-1966 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Unidentified, Undated Illegible Names and Letter Fragments, circa 1925-1972 (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Writings and Notes, 1932-1972, Series 3:; (Box 4-5; 0.5 linear feet)
  Writings and notes include draft essays, lectures, speeches, notes,lists, recommendations, annotated address book and engagement calendar. Subjects of writings include art technique, art history, Kroll's art, and the work of other artists. Lectures and speeches were generally given at art organizations such as the American Federation of Arts or at art schools and universities. Additional writings include drafts of recommendations of artists for grants, memberships, or appointment to committees. Lists of people consist of drafts of invitation lists, member lists, and mailing lists. Scattered writings by others include an essay by Julia E. Langsam describing her experience as an artist's model for Kroll and additional writings about Kroll by unknown authors.
  Writings are arranged in rough chronological order. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Annotated Typescripts, "Painting the Nude," 1963 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Autobiographical Writings, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Artist Recommendations, circa 1940s (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Lectures at Finch School, 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Speech at Worcester Art Museum, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Speech at American Federation of Arts, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Speech at Cooper Union, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lecture, "A Painter's Point of View," 1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Lecture, "Mural Paintings for Shriver Hall," circa 1956 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lecture, "The Eight," 1962 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Lectures and Speeches, 1932-1967, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - Undated Lectures and Speeches, circa 1930s-1960s, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes, 1932-1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Undated Miscellaneous Writings and Notes, circa 1930s-1960s, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 11-14)
  - Lists of People, circa 1938-1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Engagement Calendar, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Address Book, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Loose Addresses, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Julia E. Langsam, "Sitter Looks At Artist," 1965 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Writings by Others about Leon Kroll, circa 1930s, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Writings by Others, Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1957 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Legal and Financial Records, 1921-1974, Series 4:; (Box 5; 0.6 linear feet)
  Found here are contracts for Kroll's mural commissions for the U.S. Justice Department and the Worcester War Memorial, teaching contracts, including ones for the Art Students League. Additional legal documents include copyright registrations for a few of Kroll's paintings, the last will and testament for his sister Lenore Landsberger, and various leases and exhibition contracts.
  Financial documents include numerous loan forms and sales receipts for his artwork, including ones from Downtown Gallery and the Carnegie Institute. Other bills and receipts primarily deal with framing or shipping. There is also an appraisal of paintings and etchings belonging to Florence Carpenter, an art collector and a patron of Kroll's work. Ledgeres record monthly financial transactions such as art consignments, cash receipts, and cash disbursements. There is also a ledger documenting transactions for his mural commissions for the Justice Department and the Worcester War Memorial.
  Items are arranged chronologically within each folder. Portions of this series have been scanned; tax documents, stock market records, insurance documents, and notes of expenses have not been scanned.
  - Contracts for Mural Commissions, 1935-1941 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Teaching Agreements, 1934-1946 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Copyright Registrations, 1942-1944 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Last Will and Testament of Lenore Landsberger (Kroll), 1966 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Documents, 1921-1924, 1964-1974 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Artwork Loan Forms and Receipts (Box 5)
    - ACA Galleries, 1964-1968 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Carnegie Institute, 1931-1945 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Downtown Gallery, 1929-1934 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Milch Galleries, 1932-1948 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Miscellaneous, 1921-1972 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Receipts, Julius Lowy Frame and Restoration Co., 1937-1938, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Bills and Receipts, 1926-1974 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Tax Documents, 1925-1954, 1967, (Not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Stock Market Records, 1921-1962, (Not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Insurance Documents, 1926, 1969, (Not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Appraisal, Artwork belonging to Florence L. Carpenter Estate, circa 1940s (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Ledger for Mural Commissions, 1935-1941 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Ledger, 1935-1938, 1943, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Ledger, 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Ledger, 1945-1949 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Ledger, 1951-1952, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Ledger, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Ledger, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Ledger, 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Ledger, 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Notes and Lists of Expenses, 1945, 1947, 1958, 1964, (Not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, 1924-1972, Series 5:; (Box 5-6; 0.4 linear feet)
  Scattered printed materials about Kroll's career include news clippings; exhibition announcements and catalogs; postcards; invitations; brochures; and material documenting his work on murals for the Worcester War Memorial, including a catalog for an exhibition of the murals, brochures, and a map of the War Memorial auditorium. Various bulletins, news letters, and reports found here are from art organizations and the federal government.
  Material in each folder is arranged in chronological order. The bulk of this series has been scanned; postcards and reproductions of artwork have not been scanned.
  - News Clippings, 1924-1968, (6 folders) (Box 6, Folder 3-8)
  - Undated News Clippings, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1927-1972 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Worcester War Memorial Printed Material, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, Newsletters, and Reports, 1929-1970 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Blank Postcards, circa 1920s, (Not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Reproductions of Artworks, circa 1940s, (Not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1929-1966 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Photographs, circa 1900s-1960s, Series 6:; (Box 6; 0.4 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Kroll, of Kroll working in his studio, of Kroll serving for juried exhibitions, of Kroll with other artists, and of Kroll's homes. Three photographs of Kroll in his studio and working on murals are by Paul Hansen and Jane Rogers. Artists depicted in images with Kroll include John Taylor Arms, Gordon Grant, Raphael Soyer, and John Sloan, fellow exhibition jury members Isabel Bishop, Reginald Marsh, Eugene Speicher, Paul Sample, and Homer Saint-Gaudens. Also found are three photographs of Kroll's colleague and friend, Edward Bruce, and a few photographs of unidentified people, possibly family members.
  Photographs of exhibitions include those at the Art Institute of Chicago, Depauw University, and the Carnegie Institute. Photographs of artwork include paintings by Kroll and of his mural commissions, including drawings and details of the Worcester war memorial mural.
  Folders in this series are arranged according to subject matter and photographs within each folder are arranged in rough chronological order. This series is partially scanned. Photographs of artwork and duplicate photographs have not been scanned.
  - Photographs of Leon Kroll, circa 1930s-1960s, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
  - Photographs of Edward Bruce, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Unidentified People, 1940s (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Leon Kroll Homes, circa 1930-1950 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Photograph of "Whistler House," circa 1930s (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Photographs of Exhibition, Art Institute of Chicago, circa 1920s (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Slides, Exhibition at Depauw University, circa 1959, (Not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Exhibitions, circa 1935-1957 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Worcester Murals, 1938-1941, (Not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1900s-1960s, (5 folders; not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 26-30)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Others, circa 1920s-1940s, (Not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Artwork, 1911-circa 1950s, Series 7:; (Box 6; 0.3 linear feet)
  Nine sketchbooks and two folders of loose drawings done by Kroll are found here. Drawings are of figures, nudes, portraits, animals, and landscapes. The sketches are done in pencil, colored pencil, and pen and ink. The earliest sketchbook, from spring, 1911, includes typed notes regarding each of the 36 drawings. Some sketchbooks also include other handwritten notations.
  Sketchbooks are arranged in rough chronological order. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Loose Drawings, circa 1930s-1940s, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 32-33)
  - Sketchbook, 1911 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Sketchbook, circa late 1920s (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1931 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1930s-1940s, (4 volumes in 2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 37-38)
  - Sketchbook, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 40)